# 呲勺
"Zi" (sizzling sound) the spoon
# 三叔 多地道啊这个
Isn't it authentic, Sanshu
# 红绿相间 真漂亮
Colourful, Beautiful!
# 这灰了吧唧什么玩意
What's this grey-ish thing?
# 麻豆腐
Madoufu (mung bean solids, by-product of cellophane noodle production)
# 有很多人来北京说吃不惯麻豆腐
Many who come to Beijing don't like Ma Tofu at first
# 吃不惯 他慢慢的越吃越香
But they gradually get used to it and start to like the taste
# 咱们就做羊油的
We'll make one with tallow (mutton fat)
# 人家吃不习惯怎么办
What if they don't like it?
# 吃不习惯 素油炒这种技法也可以
Then we can use vegetable oil instead
# 毛豆仁儿提前入一下味儿
We give some seasoning to the shelled edamame beans
# 大料 花椒粒 盐 别的不用加
Nothing but star anise, Sichuan peppercorns, salt
# 这么简单 对
That easy? Yeah
# 好 十五分钟就行了
Alright, 15 mins should be enough
# 为了节省时间
To save some time
# 咱就先把雪里蕻焯一下水 因为它咸
We first rinse the Xuelihong in boiling water to remove some salt
(Preserved Chinese potherb mustard greens)
# 麻豆腐雪里蕻跟豆儿是绝配 离不开
Ma tofu and potherb mustard are the perfect match. Inseparable.
# 雪里蕻不能太少了
Don't put too little potherb mustard
# 咱就干焙 不放油
Let's dry fry it without oil
# 其实雪里蕻是麻豆的筋骨
Potherb mustard is the backbone of Ma Tofu
# 专业术语叫魂儿 筋骨
Technically speaking, the soul of Ma Tofu
# 煮好的豆 最好是泡个一个小时
It is the best to soak the cooked edamame in the cooking liquid for an hour
# 大料 花椒那个味儿入进去
To ensure the flavor of star anise and Sichuan peppercorns permeates through the beans
# 五香豆儿说白了就是
They are basically five-spice beans
# 熟了没有 不能糊弄我们网友
Is it cooked? Don't fool our audience
# 正好
It's just right.
# 收收水气行了
Just dry it for a bit.
# 咱们现在开始耗油
We now start to infuse the oil
# 关键是在耗油
This is the crucial part
# 这个药料咱也先给它洗一下
Wash these spices
# 有小茴香 豆蔻 香叶 辣椒 八角
Fennel seeds, cardamom, bay leaves, dried chili, star anise
# 要葱油么 葱油更好
Do you need some scallion oil? Even better!
# 我给你炸好的
I made it for you
# 好 谢谢三叔
Thank you Sanshu
# 少放点 把我的全放里了
Ok, you used it all
# 羊油 羊尾巴油
Mutton Fat, from the tail
# 再搁点葱出点葱香味
Give some fresh spring onions, for the flavor
# 把所有的料下下去
Now put all the spices into the wok
# 麻豆腐关键的是油 香香的
It's all about the oil, aromatic!
# 耗油的同时咱把口儿给它调出来
In the meantime we should start on the tofu
# 把雪里蕻加进去 豆儿
shove in the potherb mustard and beans
# 麻豆腐是什么做的
what is the tofu made of
# 绿豆 先得泡 泡完以后打碎了
Mung means. Soak, and then grind them
# 糗出来的
Let it sit until it gets slimy
# 它那个汁儿提出来
The liquid can be separated and then fermented
# 发酵完了就是豆汁
and it becomes Douzhi
(fermented mung bean milk, another traditional Beijing dish)
# 渣子就是麻豆腐
The remaining solids are the Madoufu
# 这个东西离不开黄酱 澥好的黄酱
Diluted yellow soybean sauce is a must for this dish
# 香啊是吧 层次感很强
Aromatic right? Strong, multi-dimensional scent
# 稍微提一点糖 糖提鲜 来一点
Give it a little sugar for more umami
# 酱油 胡椒粉
Soy sauce, pepper powder
# 还有秘诀 咱把炸好的葱捞出来
Secret of my recipe: take out all fried scallion
# 再切点葱末 没少用葱啊
Chop more spring onions. We are using a lot of it today.
# 突出葱香味儿
To highlight the scallion flavor
# 看见没有网友 把炸好的葱切成末
Pay attention my friends, chop the fried scallion into fine dices
# 然后拌在里头吃着香
and mix it with the dish
# 下一个节目 豆汁
for our next trick, DouZhi!
# 用豆汁澥麻豆腐 原汁原味
We used Douzhi to dilute the Madoufu. Stay true to their shared origin.
# 香 酸香
Aromatic, It smells sour but aromatic (the smell of Douzhi)
# 咱们起锅坐油 关键是油
Now we setup a wok and pour in the oil, the crucial part
# 油可以多一点没关系 不要怕油大
We can use a little more oil. Don't be afraid of using too much
# 既然做咱们就往传统上做
We are following the traditional way today.
# 想吃油少油多的自己去调整
You can use whatever amount of oil as you like
# 再一次的大量的葱花 葱香味
Again, lots of scallion. The aroma of scallion.
# 差不都了这菜
We are almost there
# 二十年专注京味菜
I've focused on Beijing cuisine for twenty years
# 讲究 香 离不开这香味
The smell of a dish is heavily emphasized. The aroma.
# 有回味啊 改小火
There will be an aftertaste. Turn down the gas
# 把麻豆腐下进去
Shove in the Madoufu
# 跟炸酱面似的 待会弄碗面条得了
Looks just like Zhajiangmian noodles' gravy. Maybe we make some noodles later
# 小火去推 必须得推
Push it over a low flame
# 待会您看 这时候有油
You can see some oil floating at the moment
# 待会就没油了 全推进去了
and it will all be pushed into the tofu a while later
# 小火慢慢熬 就跟炸酱似的
Use a low flame, just as you are making Zhajiangmian noodles' gravy
# 熬多长时间师父 一般
How long do we decoct it, master?
# 最少得二十分钟
20 minutes at least
# 要如果有时间的话 四十分钟小火
40 minutes over a low flame if you have time
# 慢慢儿推 炖透了
Push it slowly
# 多香 糗透了
Smells so good! It's cooked through
# 麻豆腐 酱 雪里蕻的香气
Ma tofu, soybean paste, the scent of potherb mustard
# 融合到一起 多棒
All mixed together beautifully! Awesome!
# 您看没油了是吧三叔
See how there is no more oil seen now, Sanshu?
# 咱们现在基本上推了二十分钟了
We've been stirring it for 20 minutes now
# 待会往外噗噗冒气 气顶勺
There will me more steam over time
# 像我这样推四十分钟（更香了）
I've stirred it for 40 minutes (gets even better)
# 来欢子推会儿 徒弟推
Come, Huanzi. Take my position for a while
Apprentice do the job
# 我推这还真是有经验
I am actually really experienced in this
# 从小一来北京学徒就开始推这个
I have been doing this (pushing Madoufu) since I was an apprentice when I first came to Beijing
# 为什么他长得帅呢
Why is he good-looking?
# 就因为推麻豆腐推的
Because he has pushed a lot of Madoufu
# 还手工灌肠 外边都是自己买
Also making homemade sausages. Other restaurants buy them from vendors
# 我们都是自己做
But we make our own sausages in-house
# 这麻豆腐不搁羊油不搁酱
If you don't make Ma Tofu with mutton fat and soybean paste
# 出不来香味
There will not be enough aroma
# 一般咱们家使的都是豆油是吧
Normally, people use soybean oil at home?
# 各种花生油 豆油都可以
Peanut oil or soybean oil is ok, too
# 就是素油 都可以
Or vegetable oil. All good.
# 素油也是这种方式
It's the same way if you choose to use vegetable oil
# 还是那句话
Once again,
# 你喜欢吃哪口儿
whatever taste you like
# 你用哪口儿油 都可以
you can use whatever oil you want. All would work
# 关键是制料油跟葱油的时候
The key is when you make the spice-infused oil and scallion-oil
# 得制好了 一通百通
You have to make that right. And once you know the principle you can apply it to other dishes.
# 这个基本形状可以了
This shape looks good enough
# 出丝了 出丝了啊
There are filaments
# 差不多得了 翻下勺
That's ok, you don't have to do it anymore
# 一看立住了
Look, it stands by itself
# 咱刨一个坑儿
We make a well on top
# 你知道这刨坑儿还不能说
Don't talk about the well!
# 待会他们就全看见了
They will see it later
# 韭菜越搁越多越香 韭菜不能少了
The more Chinese chives you put in the more aromatic it gets
# 辣椒油呢 辣椒油待会现呲
Where's the chilli oil? We will make the chilli oil.
# 欢子看你的手艺了今天
It's all on you Huanzi
# 师父考考你
Pop quiz for you:
# 这是什么油 色拉油
What's this oil? Vegetable oil
# 还是把辣椒洗一下
Let's wash the chilli first
# 洗一下油温高点没事
This way it won't burn so easily when you pour hot oil over it
# 没问题
No Problem
# 关键是这呲啦一下
Carefull, It's neck or nothing
# 呲勺
"Zi" the spoon. Make it sizzle.
# 三叔 多地道啊这个
So authentic right, Sanshu?
# 出锅喽
Ready to serve!
# 红绿相间 真漂亮
Colorful and beautiful
# 感觉怎么样三叔
How does it taste, Sanshu?
# 我有一种自豪感
I am very proud
# 太好了
Very good!
# 天上有 人间能有几回绝 是吧
This is heavenly good. How many times can you taste this as a mortal? (Chinese Idiom)
# 绝对北京味儿 做的好
Absolutely authentic Beijing flavor. Good job!
# 好 谢谢叔儿
Right, Thank you Shu!
# 太好吃了
So delicious!
# 青韭 辣椒 颜色 口味
Green Chives, Chilli, Colour, Taste
# 关键你最后那辣椒 你看见没有
The last step when you sizzle that chilli
# 那呲啦这一下 必须得到位了
that had to be done right!
# 说糊没糊 说没糊马上要糊了
It needs to be almost burnt but not.
# 那种回味
The aftertaste of that
# 韭菜的香气 辣椒的香气
The aroma of chives and chilli
# import ending.srt 00:05:47,300